<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Sidey</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2020-03-27T03:11:58-05:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name></name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>The Beauty of Jekyll</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/27/the-beauty-of-jekyll"/>
   <updated>2020-03-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/27/the-beauty-of-jekyll</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Picture the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I boot up &lt;a href=&quot;https://atom.io/&quot;&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt; to begin writing a blog post. I make a new Markdown file, hammer out a couple of paragraphs. My writing concluded, hit &lt;code&gt;Ctrl+S&lt;/code&gt; on that bad boy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do I leave the fiddling and futzing to take my slightly nerdy &lt;code&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; file and convert it into Wordpress or whatever for another day, and just head to sleep? If I were working with that kind of process, probably; I’m a bit of a lazybones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m not working with that process. In fact, I do something very different – something beautifully simple, ingrained into me from years and years of good programmer practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, first off, this &lt;code&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; file is actually saved inside of a git repo – but, okay, that’s not &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; unusual. Plenty of written materials exist on GitHub, even if we almost never actually have to bust out its more &lt;a href=&quot;https://atom.io/&quot;&gt;DerAnG&lt;/a&gt;ed history-bending features on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atom happens to be built &lt;em&gt;by&lt;/em&gt; GitHub, so I hit &lt;code&gt;Ctrl+Shift+9&lt;/code&gt; to bring up the tiny little panel where I can &lt;code&gt;Stage All Changes&lt;/code&gt;, then hit &lt;code&gt;Ctrl+Enter&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;Commit Staged Changes&lt;/code&gt; (with a cheeky &lt;code&gt;commit&lt;/code&gt; comment), and finally hit &lt;code&gt;Ctrl+Enter&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Alt+G P&lt;/code&gt; to commit and push changes to the repo. Up the pipeline it goes, to GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s something… &lt;em&gt;Odd&lt;/em&gt; about this GitHub repo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/3-27-2020-odd-repo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Why are there so many other files in here besides the `.md` one we were just editing?&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why are there so many other files in here besides the &lt;code&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; one we were just editing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that all of those &lt;code&gt;.html&lt;/code&gt; files and their ilk are what the static site generator &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jekyll&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; uses to work its magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;jekyll-a-dream-come-true&quot;&gt;Jekyll: A dream come true&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll is the kind of software I &lt;em&gt;dreamed&lt;/em&gt; about when I was just starting out in my coding journey, over a decade ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone who wants to put stuff on the web starts out by learning a bit of HTML and CSS. Maybe JS if they’re hardcore. Most people very, very quickly realize there is &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; too much HTML, CSS, and JS in any webpage of real complexity to actually dig in and understand most of it. At best our hand-authoring is used for the occasional, manual, spot check; we leave actually generating the stuff to behemoths like Wordpress and other content management systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This always bugged me growing up. I correctly felt like this was &lt;em&gt;too much power being taken away&lt;/em&gt; from me. Having grown up &lt;a href=&quot;http://catb.org/~esr/writings/taoup/&quot;&gt;reading my history&lt;/a&gt; I knew that this wasn’t the way the old hackers would have wanted things to be either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides, most of my favorite websites were (are) blogs. I don’t really need, or even want, all that complicated analytics and stuff going on behind my back most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why couldn’t there just be a computer program where I could feed it in some plain text files, maybe lightly marked up, and have it spit out a decently functional – but simple! – website? Where I wouldn’t be constrained to tossing my writing into some obscure CMS binary blog?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s exactly what Jekyll is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll, at its core, gives you a simple promise, after you get it set up (which my experience suggests takes about an afternoon, unless you really want to dive in deep and make something unique – which you can!). You focus on writing the &lt;code&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; files. Let &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt; handle actually generating a site for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And once I’m done, there’ll be a nice little &lt;code&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; folder sitting right there, filled with &lt;code&gt;.html&lt;/code&gt; files that you can open up and peruse in the leisure of your own web browser, locally, just like that first time you authored a webpage by hand. (Except they’ll probably look much, much nicer. 😉)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A match made in heaven, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;netlify-continuous-integration-for-blogs&quot;&gt;Netlify: Continuous integration for blogs&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Continuous integration” and “continuous deployment” are basically fancy programmer speak for, “I want you to do certain things &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; time I push a new commit to our GitHub branch”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I’m no pro, usually, I think of the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://travis-ci.org/&quot;&gt;Travis CI&lt;/a&gt; service when it comes to that stuff, which basically runs suites upon suites upon suites of software tests on your code-base every time you push up to the ‘hub. Naturally this requires automatically running the code you want tested in some regard, right? So it’s almost like an IFTTT trigger – “New code? Okay, recompile and run all the tests again”. Fantastic stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait a minute. Blogs don’t &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; tests they need to pass. They’re literally just words. Why might this be useful? Well, suppose you have a bunch of &lt;code&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; files, and you can generate a really spiffy site with them just by running &lt;code&gt;jekyll build&lt;/code&gt; in their parent directory…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s exactly what &lt;a href=&quot;http://netlify.com/&quot;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt; does. &lt;strong&gt;For free.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you set it up correctly (and this is considerably easy, much easier than Jekyll’s setup in fact), then &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; time you push up new content to the GitHub repo where you’re storing your &lt;code&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; blog posts, and maybe some images and stuff too, Netlify will kick into gear, generate a brand new &lt;code&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; on their end, and then &lt;strong&gt;host it for you&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;em&gt;genius&lt;/em&gt;, because those &lt;code&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt;s are, well, static! There’s very little overhead to just hosting a bunch of &lt;code&gt;.html&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;.css&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;.js&lt;/code&gt; files. Static sites by definition don’t do anything crazy server-side; any nice little effects are going to happen client-side, and that’s that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and if you happen to have a domain lying around on a place like &lt;a href=&quot;hover.com/&quot;&gt;Hover&lt;/a&gt;, all it takes to link that domain to the new static site is changing the nameservers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a blogging workflow now that brings so much &lt;em&gt;joy&lt;/em&gt; to my heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of my posts are stored and written in plain text, just like back in the days of yore where I used to use &lt;code&gt;org-mode&lt;/code&gt; to generate these kinds of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet when I push up to the ‘hub, &lt;em&gt;wizards halfway across the globe&lt;/em&gt; use Jekyll to render my little stack of plain text doohickeys into something… just… gorgeous. Absolutely stunning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t say it’s &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; good yet; I still need to figure out how to get MathJax working. But the combination of Jekyll + GitHub + Netlify + Hover for Nonstandard Deviations mgiht be my favorite Internet thing of the entire year.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
